NASIM MAHMUD NAYAN

Cell phone no: +8801742957256 Email: smnoyan670@gmail.com

Objective

Pursuing an advanced degree with dedication to Machine Learning (ML) and cyber-physical systems, driven by research passion and interdisciplinary collaboration. I aim to excel, innovate, and contribute meaningfully to my field with dedication, discipline, honesty, and teamwork.

Education

University Of Information Technology And Sciences

B.Sc. in Computer Science Engineering Overall GPA: 3.62(out of 4.0)

Honors And Awards

● Fastest problem solver: UITS Victory Day Programming Contest UITS , 2021

2nd/45: Inter-university Programming Contest
 UITS , 2022

1st/25: Inter-university PowerPoint Presentation Competition
 UITS , 2020

Employee of the month(August): Primacy infotec LTD Primacy infotec ltd,

Research Interests

Machine learning, Cyber-Physical System, Medical Cyber-Physical System, Internet of things, Healthcare, Artificial intelligence, Deep Learning.

Research Experience

UITS, Department of Computer Science and Engineering

Independent Research under Mohammad Mobarak Hossain

• Develop a machine learning-based system to predict maternal health risks.

Dhaka, Bangladesh Jan. 2022 - present

2023

- Implemented ML algorithms were used to identify patterns and risk factors associated with maternal health complications.
- Integrated Homomorphic encryption techniques to ensure secure handling and protection of patient data.

UITS, Department of Computer Science and Engineering

Independent Research under Md. Monirul Islam

 $_{ullet}$ Developed an integrated and original method to forecast illness.

Dhaka, Bangladesh July. 2022 - present

- Collaborated with team members within his research lab, 'Research Rising Lab.
- Conducting literature reviews to gather relevant research articles.

UITS, Department of Computer Science and Engineering

Independent Research under Mohammud Usama Islam

 Work on diabetes disease prediction research project using machine learning techniques.

Dhaka, Bangladesh May. 2022 - July. 2023

- Conducted data preprocessing, including data balancing and feature engineering, to enhance predictive model accuracy.
- Implemented various machine learning algorithms and fine-tuned hyperparameters to optimize model performance, presenting findings in conferences and publications.

AIUB, Department of computer science and Engineering

Independent Research under Dr. Ashraful Islam

 Conducted advanced search and evaluation of articles to investigate the application of computer vision (CV) in the medical field.

 Identified Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN) as the dominant approach in medical CV research.

Identified Computer vision is primarily utilized in surgical assistance within the medical sector domain.

Dhaka, Bangladesh June. 2023 - Sep. 2023

Professional Experience

Al Trainer | Enhancing Digital Government Economy (EDGE) Project | May 2023 - Present.

- · Conducted training sessions on AI topics, including machine learning and computer vision.
- Developed educational materials and mentored students to enhance their AI skills.
- · Collaborated with diverse students to create a supportive learning environment.

Al Engineer | Primacy Infotech Ltd | July 2023 - Present.

- Led a team in developing Al-driven tour planning tools for six historic locations in Bangladesh, streamlining itinerary creation based on user preferences.
- Launched and managed trial phases for AI tour planning tools, collecting valuable user feedback for ongoing improvements.
- Currently overseeing the development and testing of "Virtual Trail," a Computer Vision-based AR tool, for online and inshopping mall virtual t-shirt try-ons.
- Effectively managing both projects, ensuring successful coordination, development, and user testing for continuous enhancement.

Selected Undergraduate Project

Multiple disease prediction systems using machine learning

• An ML-based web application developed using the Streamlit framework allows users to monitor their real-time health condition by simply inputting values." **Live, GitHub.**

2022

E-commerce Website for Outfit only

• A website offering high-quality Outfit for purchase, designed and built using HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and PHP." Live, GitHub.

2021

Breast Cancer Detection Using Flask Api

• An ML web application developed using the Flask API framework allows users to monitor realtime cancer detection. <u>Live, GitHub</u>. 2023

Conference Paper Presentation

Nasim Mahmud Nayan, Ashraful Islam, Muhammad Usama Islam, Eshtiak Ahmed, Mohammad Mobarak Hossain, Md Zahangir Alam. Paper: "SMOTE Oversampling and Near Miss Undersampling Based Diabetes Diagnosis from Imbalanced Dataset with XAI Visualization" presented in 28th IEEE Symposium on Computers and Communications (ISCC) 2023 on a special session,9-12 July, Tunisia, North Africa 2023.

Salah uddin parbehz Shakil, Mohammad abul kashem, md. monirul Islam, **Nasim Mahmud Nayan**, jia uddin. Paper: "Investigation of Air Effluence Using IoT and Machine Learning" presented in 6th International Conference on Emerging Technologies in Computing 2023 (iCETiC '23), 17-18 August, University of Essex, Southend Campus, UK 2023.

Skills

500+ problem solve
Codeforces: NM Nayan.
Beecrowd: NMNAYAN.

Programming Language: Python, C, C++, HTML, CSS.

Machine Learning: Sklearn, Tensorflow, Pandas, Matpotib, Numpy, Openai, etc.

Research Skills: Methodology, Data Analysis, Experimental Design, Literature Review, Data Manipulation.

Framework: Streamlit, Flaskapi. **Version Control:** Git, Github

 $\textbf{Others:} \ \mathsf{Data} \ \mathsf{structures} \cdot \mathsf{Algorithms}$

Campus Activities

Junior executive | programmer hub wings at UITS computer club Jan. 2022 - Aug. 2022

Senior executive | research hub wings at UITS computer club Oct. 2022 - Jan.2023

Publications

- M. Sahidullah, N. Nayan, M. Morshed, M. Hossain, and M. U. Islam. Date fruit classification with machine learning and explainable artificial intelligence. 184, 03 2023
- The paper titled 'A Medical Cyber-Physical System for Predicting Maternal Health in Developing Countries Using Machine Learning' is currently awaiting a decision from the editor at Healthcare Analytics (Elsevier)."
- The paper titled 'A Review of Modern Methods for Safely Transmitting Pregnancy Health Information' has been accepted for G-CIDA 2023."
- The paper titled 'The Role of Computer Vision in Healthcare: A Review." is under review at the 2023 5th International Conference on Sustainable Technologies for Industry 5.0 (STI, 2023)."
- The paper titled 'An IoT Based Real-Time Environmental Monitoring System for Developing Areas' is under review at Journal of Advanced Research in Applied Sciences and Engineering Technology"
- The paper titled 'Parkinson's Disease Prediction Utilizing Explainable AI Techniques' is currently under review by 'The Journal of Supercomputing(Springer).'
- The paper titled 'Enhancing the Security of Pregnancy Health Data Transmission through Homomorphic Encryption: An Advanced Mode' has been accepted for inclusion in the book chapter 'Internet of Things: Applications and Technology,' which is part of CRC Press, Taylor and Francis Group, and indexed in Scopus."

References

Mohammad Mobarak Hossain, Associate Professor & Dean

School of Engineering University of South Asia

Email: mobarak.hossain@southasiauni.ac.bd

Mobile: +880 1715-659054

Dr. Ashraful Islam, Assistant Professor,

Department of C.S.E,

Independent University, Bangladesh,

Email: ashraful@iub.edu.bd Mobile: +880 1911-626900 Jia Uddin, Assistant Professor,

Al and Big Data Department, Endicott College, Woosong University, Daejeon, South Korea.

Email: jia.uddin@wsu.ac.kr **Mobile:** 0082-1072620727

Muhammad Usama Islam, Lecturer on study leave,

Asian University of Bangladesh, and Graduate Teaching Assistant, University of Louisiana at Lafayette, USA **Email:** usamaislam@iut-dhaka.edu

Mobile: +1 (337) 349-6158